PROFESSOR: That's an algorithm
called value iteration.
You can think of this as basically
building your computation from the
bottom up, all the way up to the top,
where you will receive the computation
that expectimax would have done, but
with a whole lot less work, assuming
we have a small number of states.
So what does value iteration do?
Here's the algorithm.
It's like building that cake.
You begin at the bottom with V0.
And for every state, V0 is 0.
There are no time steps left.
And that means there are
no rewards left.
So what does this actually
look like in code?
It is a vector.
There's a 0 for every state
in this vector.
So this is different than expectimax,
which you think about as
computing for one state.
This is all states.
It's a vector of 0's.
Let's say we've computed V sub k.
And at the beginning, that's V0.
So at any point we know, you tell me
any state, and I will tell you what
happens if you run a depth
k expectimax search.
We have that cached.
It's in a vector.
What we're going to do is we're
going to do one ply of
expectimax from each state.
So we're going to visit state
by state and run a tiny
little expectimax search.
Except this expectimax search
is going to be super fast.
Let's see what it does.
What it's going to do
is start at state s.
It's going to consider all actions a,
just like a max node always does.
That's reflected in this
equation right here.
We're going to max over all values a.
Then for each of the chance nodes s
comma a, the queue states, we're going
to now have to consider
every result s prime.
That's reflected here.
Again, it's this average over all of the
s prime outcomes of the action a.
And for each s prime, it has some
weight, T s, a, s prime.
For each of these s primes, we then look
up the instantaneous reward for
that one step.
And then we recurse.
But the recursion is into
an expectimax tree that
we've already computed.
So we'll add in the instantaneous
reward and the recursion.
But the recursion won't
actually happen.
Because the recursion has already been
computed, and that's V sub k.
We already have that entire
vector for every state.
And so what does this actually do?
It goes from 0 to 1 to 2.
And we keep going until
we decide to stop.
When are we going to stop?
What is that magic value of k?
We can either know that our goal is
100, and we're going to stop.
That would be fine.
But we can do something
even better now.
Because we're going bottom up, we can
keep doing this until it converges.
And if this is the kind of MDP where
you have to go very deeply into the
tree, we just run it for longer.
And we can tell convergence
when we see it.
We'll talk about that in a second.
So we have this algorithm.
We start with V0.
We do this update for every level.
How expensive is each iteration
of this update?
Well, what do we do?
Well, we need to compute a
quantity for each state.
So that's a factor of s.
We're going to do this update
for each state s.
Then for each state, we
do a mini expectimax.
We have to consider every a.
So there's going to be some for-loop
over actions, just like a max node
always has.
Then there's going to be a sum
over resulting states.
Which in the worst case, any possible
state could result, though it's often
much sparser than that.
And so we get another for-loop over
states, which is another factor of s.
So every iteration of this costs s
squared times the number of actions.
Is that good or bad?
Well, it's good in that it doesn't grow
with the number of iterations
like expectimax grows with the depth.
It's bad in that expectimax doesn't
have to touch every state if it
doesn't go too deep.
This always touches every state.
So it's all about the trade-off of how
many states you have and how connected
they are and how deep you need
to go into the tree.
We have a theorem that says that this
process, value iteration starting at
V0 and working your way up to larger
time-limited V sub k, will converge to
unique optimal values.
And the basic idea of this is that the
approximations get better and better
as you go deeper into the tree.
And in particular, the policy may
converge long before the values do.
Let's see an example that will show
us both that issue of the policies
converging fast and what
this actually does.
Let's take a look.
We start at the bottom.
We start with V sub 0.
That's our base case.
And we always know that if there's no
rewards left, then for every state, we
can put in a big 0 for the value.
Whatever policy you have, you're going
to get 0 from that point on because
there is no "that point on."
Let's think about V sub 1.
We have to visit each of
the possible states.
So we're going to do this three times.
And for each one, we're going to
do a little expectimax search.
Except only one more time step will
happen, and then we'll plug in V0.
So let's do blue, the
cool state, first.
So let's think about this.
You are in this state here,
the cool state.
And we do a little expectimax search.
Again, as an equation, that's this.
In practice, it means we think,
all right, we have to
consider the two actions.
It could be the best thing
to do is go slow.
Or the best thing to do is go fast.
If I go slow, what score will I get?
I'll get a plus 1 in the next time
step, and then V0, which is 0.
If I go fast, I'll get a plus
2 for either outcome.
And then the various
states will be 0's.
So what should I do?
I should go fast.
I'll get a 2 there.
Similarly from the warm state, in one
more step I've got the choice of going
slow and receiving a plus 1 or going
fast and receiving a minus 10.
Simple choice there.
You go slow and you receive a plus 1.
And from overheated, you have
no actions available.
So we can just say that
that's still 0.
All of the interesting
action comes at V2.
And it's not over here.
Because for overheated,
you still have 0.
So let's think about how
we fill these in.
Let's do the cool state first.
I've got two possibilities
from this expectimax.
Either the best thing to do is to
go slow and then act optimally
thereafter, meaning plug in V1.
Let's figure out that.
So I break out this computation.
If I go slow, then what
am I going to get?
I'm going to get a 1 as an
instantaneous reward.
And if there's no discount, then
I'm going to land back at cool.
And then I'm going to plug in
V1 of cool, which is 2.
And I get 3.
Or I could go fast.
If I go fast, I receive
a 2 instantaneously.
But what happens after that?
Well, I have a 50/50 chance of plugging
in this number, because I got
sent back to cool, and a 50/50 chance
of plugging in this number.
And so what I end up with
here is plus 1.5.
And if I work all of that
out, now I have 3.5.
And if I work that out for the warm
state, it'll come out to 2.5.
And so what do we see?
We see, one, that as I go further
up, the numbers are increasing.
And that makes sense because as I have
more time steps in this MDP, I can get
more rewards.
I also see that at every layer, it's
better to be in the cool state than to
be in the warm state.
And of course it's better.
Because you can then safely go fast.
Now, you can look at this, and
you can probably figure
out the optimal policy.
This is designed so the optimal policy
is if you're cool, go fast.
And once you warm up, you go slow.
And you never risk overheating.
Now, that optimal policy of from cool
go fast, from warm go slow, at what
point did we find it?
We actually found it already at V1.
These numbers 2 and 1 already reflect
when you're cool go fast and when
you're warm go slow.
But it takes longer for the values to
actually figure out how good that is.
Now, in general, V1 is not enough
to find the best policy.
And in particular, this MDP, because
there's no discount, the Vs aren't
going to converge.
So how do we know this thing
is going to converge?
We're computing these V sub k
vectors, and how do we know
they're going to converge?
Well first of all, we don't.
Because if there's no discount, and the
rewards are all positive, and the
game's never going to end, like for
racing, the values are infinite.
And you're never going to get there.
But there are cases where we can
show that it will converge.
One case is when the underlying tree
has maximum depth M. That means for
some reason, for some knowledge about
this particular MDP, you can say that
it will end after M steps.
There's no possible sequence of actions
and outcomes that lasts longer
than M. Well, then it seems reasonable
that this should converge, because
once I hit VM, I've done the full
expectimax search, and any further
iterations will do nothing.
But that's easy case.
The general case about why this usually
converges is because usually
the discount is less than 1 And all I'm
going to do is sketch this proof.
But it goes something like this.
In value iteration, we
compute V sub k.
And then in the next step, we
compute V sub k plus 1.
So we can think of that here as we're
going from V sub k to V sub k plus 1.
And we're doing this for all states.
But let's think about
a specific state.
V sub k and V sub k plus 1 both
represent expectimax searches, except
the V sub k plus 1 search goes
deeper by one layer.
Now, I can imagine the V sub k1 also
goes deeper by one layer, except that
bottom layers filled with 0's.
That will give me the equivalent
computation.
So I've got these two things.
And I can imagine they're both of depth
k plus 1, except for V sub k,
that last layer is just 0.
So how can you be different?
We're doing some computation
along these trees.
Well, what's the difference?
What's down here?
Well, what's down here is a mix
of stuff that's the actual
rewards from the MDP.
But at best, they're all the
maximum reward possible.
At worst, it's all the minimum
reward possible.
And that means that V sub k, which
plugged in 0, we could imagine it
either having R MIN or R MAX down
there, and V sub k plus 1 is in
between those things.
And because of that, we know that the
difference from that last layer is
really the maximum reward.
And because you're buried k plus 1
layers down, everything down there's
discounted by gamma to the k.
And that means V sub k and
V sub k plus 1 can't
actually be all that different.
Because that last layer can
only be so big or small.
And it's squashed down by
the discount anyway.
What this means is that as k increases,
for any given state, the
difference between V k and V k plus 1
has to shrink exponentially fast.
And that means it's going to converge,
provided gamma is less than 1.
How fast it converges depends
on the effect of depth.
And the effect of depth is either the
actual depth of the tree or, as gamma
gets closer to one, the effect of depth,
or the horizon, increases.